Welcome to Sentinel — an automated war damage detection
system built at the University of Florida.
Sentinel uses freely available Sentinel-2 satellite imagery
from the European Space Agency — freely available at 10
metres per pixel — to detect and quantify the destruction of
civilian infrastructure in active conflict zones.
The pipeline has five stages. Stage one: acquisition.
Sentinel-2 multispectral imagery is fetched from Google
Earth Engine for two time windows — a pre-war baseline and a
post-conflict analysis window. Cloud masking is applied via
the QA60 quality band.
Stage two: preprocessing. The full satellite image is sliced
into overlapping 256 by 256 pixel patches, normalised to
reflectance values, and stacked into six-channel tensors
that pair the pre-war and post-war RGB bands side by side.
Stage three: inference. A U-Net with a ResNet-34 encoder
runs sliding-window segmentation across the entire image,
producing full-resolution probability maps. A Vision
Transformer then classifies each region as undamaged, newly
damaged, or pre-existing damage.
Stage four: the FastAPI backend vectorises the damage label
map into geo-referenced polygons and caches the result to
disk, so repeat queries return in under one second. Stage
five: a React frontend renders everything on an interactive
canvas.
Let's see it live. Here is the Sentinel interface.
The green live-data indicator confirms the FastAPI backend
is online and all models are loaded.
I'll select Kharkiv, Ukraine — a city that experienced
intense urban warfare starting in February 2022.
The date range is pre-populated: March through August 2022,
covering the first six months of the conflict.
Let me flag hospitals and schools as the infrastructure
types we want to highlight.
Clicking Analyze. Because Kharkiv is a pre-cached location,
the full pipeline result returns almost instantly.
The loading screen steps through each pipeline stage — cloud
masking, U-Net segmentation, ViT temporal classification,
zone vectorisation, and report generation.
And here are the results. The satellite map shows post-war
Kharkiv with the damage mask overlaid. Red zones mark areas
newly damaged since the conflict began. Orange zones
indicate pre-existing damage already present before the war.
The metrics panel shows 2,266 damage zones flagged across
the city, with over 69,000 newly damaged pixels and more
than 1.1 million pixels of pre-existing damage.
You can click any damage zone to open a detail popup showing
its classification, confidence score, and geo-coordinates.
The confidence threshold slider on the left filters zones in
real time. Raising it removes lower-confidence predictions
and focuses the map on the areas the model is most certain
about.
Now let me show you Mariupol — a port city that suffered
some of the most intense urban destruction of the entire
conflict.
Mariupol shows over 23 percent of surveyed pixels with some
form of damage — compared to 18 percent for Kharkiv —
reflecting the near-total urban destruction the city
experienced.
On the evaluation side, the balanced U-Net checkpoint
achieves a Mean I-o-U of 0.838 on the combined test set,
with 91.4 percent overall pixel accuracy. Damaged pixel
recall is 96.5 percent — the model catches almost all real
damage with very few misses.
Kharkiv scores a Mean I-o-U of 0.849. Mariupol is lower at
0.673, reflecting the smaller amount of Mariupol training
data — an area for continued improvement as more imagery
becomes available.
Sentinel is open source, built on PyTorch, FastAPI, and
React, and designed to scale to any conflict zone where
Sentinel-2 imagery is available. Thank you for watching.